Finding aid to Record Group 9. Photographs, of the YWCA of the U.S.A. records SSC.MS.00324.RG9
Sophia Smith Collection
- Prints and negatives, 1
  - Program, E
    - Sports: Miscellaneous, circa 1895-1989 (Box 1033, Folder 3)
      Photographs highlighting sports and recreation program for women and girls at community YWCA of the USA associations.
      Sports for women; Sports for girls; Recreation; Outdoor recreation; Archery; Baseball; Basketball for women; Bowling; Skating
    - Sports: Basketball, 1999 (Box 1033, Folder 4)
      Photographs of basketball programs for middle school girls including a clinic at Cleveland State University and photographs with the handwritten caption "Nike Girls Basketball '99," possibly a Nike basketball clinic.
      Basketball for girls; Sports for girls; Cleveland State University; Cleveland Rockers (Basketball team)
    - Sports: Bicycling, 1896-1971 (Box 1033, Folder 5)
      Photographs of women and girls participating in bicycling activities at community YWCA of the USA associations.
      Cycling for women; Physical fitness for women; Sports for women
    - Sports: Dance, circa 1950-1989 (Box 1033, Folder 6-7)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA dance classes and groups including classes in contemporary, traditional, and modern styles.
      Dancers; Physical fitness for women; Dance -- Study and teaching; Dance for children; Dance for women
    - Sports: Fencing, circa 1935; undated (Box 1033, Folder 8)
      Photographs of fencing instruction programs.
      Fencing -- Training; Physical fitness for women; Sports for women; Fencing for women
    - Sports: Golf, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1033, Folder 9)
      Photographs of golf instruction at community associations of the YWCA of the USA.
      Golf -- Study and teaching; Golf for women; Sports for women; Physical fitness for women
    - Sports: Horseback riding, circa 1948-1970 (Box 1033, Folder 10)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA horseback riding activities.
      Horsemanship; Sports for women; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
    - Sports: Racquet sports, circa 1920-1999 (Box 1033, Folder 11)
      Photographs of tennis and badminton programs and activities for youth and adults through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Sports for women; Sports for girls; Badminton (Game); Tennis; Tennis for children
    - Sports: Self-defense and martial arts, circa 1950-1979 (Box 1033, Folder 12)
      Photographs of martial arts and self defense classes for women and youth through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Sports for women; Self-defense for women; Martial arts
    - Sports: Skiing, circa 1955-1976 (Box 1033, Folder 13)
      Photographs of ski instruction and activities through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Sports for women; Skiing for women
    - Sports: Swimming, circa 1950-1989 (Box 1033, Folder 14-17, Box 1034, Folder 1-2)
      Photographs of swimming and water safety classes, programs and activities for children and adults through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Photographed programs include swimming for fun, exercise, or sport, as well as water introduction for infants, and classes for children and adults with disabilities.
      Swimming photographs are arranged as follows:
      Children's classes
      Competition and meets
      Skin diving and water safety
      Handicapped
      Swimming -- Study and teaching; Swimming; Swimming for children; Swimming for infants; Sports for women; Physical fitness for women; Aquatic sports -- Safety measures; Skin diving; Swimming for people with disabilities
    - Sports: Water sports, undated (Box 1034, Folder 3)
      Photographs of boating and water skiing activities through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Aquatic sports; Water skiing; Boats and boating; Sports for women
    - Recreation: General, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 4)
      Two photographs of the YWCA of Princeton, New Jersey's Friday Club (a club for women over 60) and a photograph of children participating in a pie eating contest at the YWCA of Duluth Minnesota.
    - Recreation: Canteens, circa 1940-1978 (Box 1034, Folder 5)
      Photographs of canteens for teenages through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Canteens offered a place for socializing, dances, and fun.
      Teenage girls; Teenage boys; Recreation; Recreation centers
    - Recreation: Miscellaneous classes, circa 1950-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 6)
      Photographs of selected classes for women through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Photographed classes include personal development, motorcycle defensive driving, and auto mechanics.
      Adult education of women; Continuing education; Motorcycling -- Safety measures; Automobiles -- Maintenance and repair
    - Recreation: Cooking classes, circa 1900-1976 (Box 1034, Folder 7)
      Photographs of cooking and baking classes for children and adults through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Cooking -- Study and teaching; Continuing education; Adult education of women
    - Recreation: Craft classes, circa 1950-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 8-9)
      Photographs of craft and arts classes and activities for women and children through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Photographed activities include ceramics, stained glass, painting, and an assortment of craft activities for children.
      Continuing education; Adult education of women; Handicraft; Handicraft for children; Pottery; Basket making; Handicraft -- Study and teaching
    - Recreation: Group work classes, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 10)
      Publicity photograph used to promote a class on conflict resolution.
      Conflict management
    - Recreation: Language classes, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1034, Folder 11)
      Photographs of language learning classes through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Language and languages -- Study and teaching; Continuing education; Adult education of women
    - Recreation: "Mr. and Mrs. Fixit" classes, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1034, Folder 12)
      Photographs of "Mr. and Mrs. Fixit" classes for husband and wives to learn mechanic and repair skills together.
      Adult education of women; Continuing education; Do-it-yourself work; Automobiles -- Maintenance and repair
    - Recreation: Painting and sculpture classes, circa 1901-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 13)
      Photographs of painting and sculpture classes for women and children through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Continuing education; Adult education of women; Pottery; Sculpture; Painting
    - Recreation: Sewing, needlework, and millinery classes, circa 1900-1929 (Box 1034, Folder 14)
      Photographs of sewing, dressmaking, millinery, and needle craft classes through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Continuing education; Adult education of women; Sewing; Millinery; Knitting; Handicraft -- Study and teaching
    - Recreation: Sewing, knitting, macramé, and weaving classes, circa 1960-1989 (Box 1034, Folder 15)
      Photographs of sewing, dressmaking, macremé, knitting, and weaving classes offered through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Adult education of women; Continuing education; Knitting; Sewing; Macramé; Weaving; Handicraft -- Study and teaching
    - Recreation: Woodworking and home repair classes, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 16)
      Photographs of home repair, woodworking and home repair classes offered through the YWCA of the USA and its community associations.
      Adult education of women; Continuing education; Do-it-yourself work; Woodwork
    - Recreation: Dances, circa 1950-1989 (Box 1034, Folder 17)
      Photographs of square dancing and folk dancing activities at YWCA of the USA community associations.
      Recreation; Square dancing; Folk dancing
    - Recreation: Games, circa 1960-1979 (Box 1034, Folder 18)
      Photographs of youth and adults enjoying games at YWCA of the USA community associations and events. Photographed games include card games, bingo, checkers, and pool.
      Recreation; Games
    - Recreation: Libraries and reading (Box 1034, Folder 19)
      Photographs and one illustration depicting library and reading activities.
      Libraries; Reading
    - Recreation: Parties and events, circa 1900-1989 (Box 1035, Folder 1-2)
      Photographs of special events and parties in the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Most of the photographed activities centered around food including banquets, picnics, and special dinners.
      Special events; Parties; Dinners and dining
    - Music, circa 1963-1992 (Box 1035, Folder 3)
      Music played a vital role for children and adults in the YWCA of the USA and its community associations throughout its history as part of club programming, conferences and classes. Photographed activities include group singing, singing and guitar lessons, camp singing, and singing with children.
      Music -- Instruction and study; Music and children; Women in music
    - Pageantry and drama, circa 1910-1976 (Box 1035, Folder 4-6)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA and community association pageants, dramas, water pageants, and water carnivals. Pageantry was used in the YWCA of the USA for fun, expression, interpretation of YWCA program, and entertainment. Photographed activities include, tableaus, skits, dramas and rehearsals, water carnivals, water pageants celebrating the one hundredth anniversary of the YWCA, drama workshops and lessons, and dances.
      Synchronized swimming; Theater; Children's theater; Tableaux; Recreation
    - Religion, circa 1915-1979 (Box 1035, Folder 7-8)
      Photographs highlighting the religious aspects of the program of the YWCA of the USA and its community associations. Photographed activities include bible studies, vespers, prayers, and ceremonies. General religious activities are followed by photographs of Christmas decorating, hanging of the greens, and additional Christmas celebration.
      Christmas; Women -- Religious life; Christmas greens
    - World War I: War work staff, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 1)
      Photographs of national domestic and international war work staff from the YWCA of the USA.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; YWCA of the U.S.A.. War Work Council
    - World War I: Parades, circa 1917-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 2)
      Photographs of women and young women's Christian association members participating in parades. Identified photographs include images of YWCA staff on their way to being stationed in Europe, liberty bond parades, Lincoln Motor girls, and Liberty Motor girls.
      Liberty bonds; Parades; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations
    - World War I: Patriotic League and homefront activities, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 3-5)
      Photographs of women participating in Patriotic League and homefront activities in support of World War I war work efforts. Patriotic League activities include women knitting, sewing, collecting goods, making candles, and supporting stationed men. Additional photographed activities include a automobile repair class in Lynchburg, Virginia and instruction in wireless communications. Wireless class photographs depict women learning how to use a wireless in addition to women instructing men.
      Patriotic League and homefront activities photographs are arranged as follows:
      Automobile class, Lynchburg, Virginia
      Wireless class
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Automobiles -- Maintenance and repair; Telegraph, Wireless -- Study and teaching; World War, 1914-1918 -- Communications
    - World War I: Signal Corps, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 6)
      Posed group and candid photographs of women Signal Corps members and trainees. Captioned photographs indicate that women were trained at YWCA of the USA facilities, housed at YWCA's as they came through New York, and housed at American YWCA hostels in France.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Communications; United States. Army. Signal Corps
    - World War I: Yeomanettes, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 7)
      Photographs of Yeomanettes, female Yeomen in the Navy during World War I. Photographs are of Yeomanettes in Bremerton, Washington and Bush Terminal, New York and captions indicate that many were served by YWCA of the USA clubs.
      Yeomen (F); World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; United States. Navy
    - World War I: Hostess houses, general, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 8)
      Photographs of model hostess houses in addition to photographs of hostess house staff and activities at identified and unidentified hostess houses.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects; Soldiers -- Recreation
    - World War I: Hostess houses, California, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 9)
      Photographs of food service and leisure activities at hostess houses at Camps Kearny and Fremont in California.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects; California, United States; Camp Kearny (Calif.); Camp Fremont (Calif.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Florida, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 10-11)
      Photographs of hostess houses in Florida at Camp Johnston, Carlstrom Field, and Dorr Field. Photographs include images of house staff, leisure and food service activities, facilities, and buildings.
      World War I: Hostess houses, Florida photographs are arranged as follows:
      Camp Johnston
      Carlstrom Field, Dorr Field
      World War, 1939-1945 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; Soldiers -- Recreation; Florida, United States; Camp Gordon Johnston (Fla.); Carlstrom Field (Fla.); Dorr Field (Fla.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Georgia, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 12)
      Photographs of the YWCA hostess house at Camp Gordon, Georgia.
      Georgia, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Camp Gordon (DeKalb County, Ga.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Kansas, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 13)
      Two photographs from the YWCA hostess house at Camp Funston, a photograph of Tsianina Redfeather and a photograph of soldiers in front of the house. The caption of the second photograph indicates that this was a hostess house serving African American military and their family and friends.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; Kansas, United States; Fort Riley (Kan.); Tsianina, 1882-1985
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Kentucky, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 14)
      Photographs of the YWCA hostess house at Camp Zachary Taylor, Kentucky. Several photographs identify the hostess house as the Information Bureau and several specify it as the "Information Bureau for the 'flu' epidemic."
      Influenza Epidemic, 1918-1919; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Kentucky, United States; Camp Zachary Taylor (Ky.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, New Jersey, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 15)
      Photographs of YWCA hostess house buildings, interiors, and leisure activities at Camp Dix, New Jersey. Photographs include images of the separate hostess house for the African American soldiers.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; Soldiers -- Recreation; New Jersey, United States; Camp Dix (N.J.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, New York, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 16-18)
      Photographs of YWCA hostess houses in New York State and three in New York City. Photographs include images of leisure activities, registration, staff, facilities, family visitation and facilitites, and visitors. The hostess house at Camp Upton, Yaphank, Long Island specifies that it is for African American military and visitors.
      New York hostess house photographs are arranged as follows:
      Camp Upton
      West 51st Street, East 52nd Street, and Lexington Ave.
      Plattsburgh
      New York, New York, United States; Plattsburgh, Clinton, New York, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- Social aspects; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; Camp Upton (N.Y.)
    - Hostess Houses: Interior of 41st St. and Lexington Ave., NY City; Ellington Field (Texas) Hostess House staff group, 14 Sep 1918; army camp (idenfication broken off) with Hostess House site marked; exterior of Hostess House, Michigan, 1918; tea in a YWCA Hut; Industrial Service Center Library, Chicago; Yeomanettes, Puget Sound Navy Yard (Box 1050, Folder 3)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, North Carolina, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 19)
      Photographs of YWCA hostess houses in North Carolina at Camp Green and Oteen General Hospital including photographs of facilities, surrounding areas, and staff. and
      North Carolina, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Camp Greene (N.C.); United States. Army. General Hospital No. 19 (Oteen, Asheville, N.C.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Ohio, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 20)
      Photographs of YWCA hostess houses in Ohio at Camp Sherman and Wilbur Wright Field. Photographs include interior and exterior shots, leisure activities, staff, and residents.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; Ohio, United States; Camp Sherman (Ohio); Wright-Patterson Air Force Base (Ohio)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Pennsylvania, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 21)
      Photographs of the YWCA hostess house at Camp Crane, Allentown, Pennsylvania.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Pennsylvania, United States; Camp Crane (Pa.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Puerto Rico, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 22)
      Photographs of the YWCA hostess house building at Camp Las Casas, San Juan, Puerto Rico.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Puerto Rico, United States; Camp Las Casas (San Juan, P.R.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Rhode Island, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 23)
      Photograph of the YWCA hostess house building at the Naval Training Station, Newport, Rhode Island.
      Rhode Island, United States; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Naval Station Newport (R.I.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, South Carolina, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 24)
      Photographs of YWCA hostess houses in South Carolina at Camp Jackson, Camp Sevier, Camp Wadsworth, and Parris Island. Photographs include images of buildings, facilities, staff, guests, and dedications.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; South Carolina, United States; Camp Jackson (S.C.); Camp Sevier (S.C.); Camp Wadsworth (Spartanburg, S.C.); Parris Island (S.C.: Recruit depot)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Georgia, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 25)
      Photograph of the YWCA hostess house at Fort Oglethorpe in Georgia.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; Georgia, United States; Fort Oglethorpe (Ga.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Texas, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1036, Folder 26-28, Box 1037, Folder 1-2)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA hostess houses in Texas including images of interiors, exteriors, and rooms in use.
      Texas hostess house photographs are arranged as follows:
      Camp Bowie (Fort Worth)
      Camp Logan (Houston)
      Ellington Field (Houston)
      Camp MacArthur and Rich Field (Waco)
      Camp Stanley (Leon Springs) and Camp Travis (San Antonio)
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Texas, United States; Camp Bowie (Fort Worth, Tex.); Camp Logan (Tex.); Ellington Field Joint Reserve Base (Tex.); Camp MacArthur (Tex.); Rich Field (Tex.); Camp Stanley (Tex.); Camp Travis (Tex.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Virginia, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 3-4)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA hostess houses in Virginia at Camp Lee, Camp A.A. Humphreys, and the Marine Signal Corps, Quantico. Photographs include interior and exterior shots as well as images of the rooms in use.
      World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Virginia, United States; Camp Lee (Va.); Fort Belvoir (Va.); Marine Corps Base Quantico (Va.)
    - World War I: Hostess houses, Washington, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 5-7)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA hostess houses in Washington state. Photographs include interior and exterior shots as well as images of the rooms in use.
      Washington hostess house photographs are arranged as follows:
      Camp Lewis (American Lake)
      Navy Yard (Bremerton)--combination hostess house and club house
      Vancouver Barracks (Vancouver)--combination hostess house and club house
      World War, 1914-1918 -- War work; World War, 1914-1918 -- Women; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; Soldiers -- Recreation; Yeomen (F); Washington, United States; Vancouver Barracks (Wash.); Naval Station Bremerton (Wash.); Camp Lewis (Wash.)
    - World War I: Housing and recreation, circa 1914-1920 (Box 1037, Folder 8)